<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- $Id: general,v 1.2 2019/03/03 20:54:13 jim Exp $ -->
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2137 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2137.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2845 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2845.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3022 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3022.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6146 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6146.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6147 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6147.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6950 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6950.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7858 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7871 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7871.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8446 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8484 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8484.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8499 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml">

<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?><!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-dlr-doh-deploy-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->
<front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="draft-reid-doh-deploy">
	   DNS over HTTPS (DoH) Deployment Considerations 
    </title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->


    <author fullname="John Dickinson" initials="J" surname="Dickinson">
      <organization>Sinodun Internet Technologies Ltd</organization>
       <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Oxford Science Park</street>
          <city>Oxford</city>
           <code>OX4 4GA</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jad@sinodun.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J" surname="Livingood">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
        <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1800 Arch Street</street>
          <city>Philadelphia</city>
          <code>PA 19118</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jason_livingood@comcast.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jim Reid" initials="J" surname="Reid">
      <organization>RTFM llp</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>St Andrews House</street>
          <city>382 Hillington Road</city>
          <region>Glasgow</region>
          <code>G51 4BL</code>
          <country>Scotland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jim@rfc1035.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2019" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

     <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>

    <workgroup>DoH</workgroup>

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
	The development of DNS over HTTPS (DoH), defined in RFC8484, introduces a major change to
	the way in which devices and applications are able to use the Domain Name System. DoH traffic
	uses HTTP over a TLS session. DoH clients and servers can use HTTP primitives to request and
	supply DNS data instead of conventional DNS queries and responses using port 53. This
	presents a number of challenges, including new risks and security concerns, for those
	operating and running IP-based networks.
      </t>
      <t>
	The objective of this document is to describe these challenges and provide advice on how to
	minimise their impact.
      </t>
    </abstract>

</front>

<middle>

  
<section title="Introduction">
    <t>
      This document is focussed on DoH deployment issues. Several of these issues also occur in 
      other DNS transports. However, the authors feel that, at this time, consideration of other
      transports should be made in other documents and in the appropriate working groups.
    </t>
    <t>
      At present, most traditional DNS traffic is not encrypted. This can pose a privacy challenge for
      Internet users, because their access to named network resources can potentially be tracked
      through their DNS queries. In principle, any network element along the path between the user
      and resolver could observe this unencrypted traffic. DoH eliminates this problem by using TLS
      to encrypt the queries and responses that are made. These use HTTP rather than the
      conventional DNS protocol. Furthermore DoH traffic can be intermingled with other HTTPS traffic,
      making it difficult for an eavesdropper to monitor DNS traffic or even be aware that it is
      taking place.
    </t>
    <t>
      A new model of DNS usage is created with DoH. A DoH server takes on the role of the recursive
      resolving server in conventional DNS. DoH clients send DNS queries to DoH servers over DoH
      instead of plaintext DNS queries to a conventional recursive resolving server. This DoH server
      is likely to be operated and controlled by a third party - i.e. not whoever operates and
      controls the existing recursive resolver DNS servers in some network. That in turn disrupts
      the long standing and well understood trust relationships in traditional DNS.
    </t>
</section>


<section title="Terminology">
  <t>
    DoH Server: A server supporting the DNS over HTTPS is called a "DoH server" to differentiate it
    from a "DNS server" (one that only provides DNS service over one or more of the other transport
    protocols standardised for DNS).  Similarly, a client that supports the DNS over HTTPS is called
    a "DoH client". The DoH server is a recursive resolver, handling DNS queries from end users/devices, 
	  rather than an authoritative DNS server.
  </t>
  <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
    "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
    <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
</section>


<section title="Contrasting DoH and Conventional DNS">
  <t>
    With conventional DNS today, using UDP or TCP port 53, most users are assigned the IP addresses
    of several recursive resolvers via DHCP or similar network bootstrapping mechanism. These are
    usually the IP addresses of recursive resolvers that are administered by the network
    operator. Users sometimes also change to third-party recursive resolvers. In some cases, they
    may even operate their own local resolver.
  </t>
  <t>
    RFC 8484 defines the protocol for DNS over HTTPS (DoH). When DoH is used, client and server DNS
    traffic is encrypted using a TLS channel, typically to port 443. DoH clients will have little
    need for conventional DNS apart from an initial bootstrap query to find the IP addresses of a
    suitable DoH server. This will mean the bulk of their DNS resolver traffic would bypass an
    operator's DNS resolver infrastructure because that traffic will make use of the resolver
    service provided by the DoH server.
  </t>
  <t>
    DoH displaces the traditional DNS client-server model of clients making queries and waiting for
    a reply from a server.
  </t>
</section>


<section title="DoH Impact on Existing DNS Behaviour">
  <section title="DNS servers using Access Control Lists">
       <t>
	When a DoH server performs the role of a recursive resolving DNS server, it queries other
	DNS or DoH servers to resolve the queries received from DoH clients. These outbound queries
	will use a source IP address of the DoH server, not the originating client. This may
	sometimes cause operational or security problems, for instance when the DoH server queries
	another DoH or DNS server that uses access control lists based on source IP address. In this
	case, the ACL applies to the DoH server and not the original DoH client. That can mean the
	DoH client eventually gets a different response than if it made the query itself. In
	particular, this may be a problem for IXFR or AXFR queries because authoritative DNS servers
	commonly use ACLs to restrict these queries.
       </t>
       <t>
       This problem becomes more acute for dynamic updates <xref target="RFC2137">RFC
       2137</xref>. If an ACL-based on source IP address is used to accept or reject these requests,
       it will be the address of the DoH server rather than the DoH client which determines the
       outcome. However Transaction Signatures (TSIG) <xref target="RFC2845">RFC2845</xref> are more
       commonly used for authenticating dynamic update requests. It is therefore essential for DoH
       servers to ensure that TSIG resource records received from DoH clients are included in
       outgoing requests. DoH servers MUST ensure TSIG resource records included in any requests
       received from DoH clients are included whenever the DoH server has to contact another DoH or
       DNS server to satisfy that request. Similarly, DoH servers MUST return to DoH clients any TSIG
       resource records that are received from DNS or DoH servers.
       </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Split DNS">
       <t>
	Split DNS configurations <xref target="RFC8499">RFC8499</xref> are widely used, particularly
	in enterprise networks. These have an internal name space which is not visible to the public
	Internet. Resolving DNS servers in such networks are configured to only provide answers for
	this name internal space to requests from clients on the enterprise network. Applications and
	devices making DoH requests on networks which use split DNS will not be able to access these
	internal names unless their requests are sent to a suitably configured DoH server. This
	probably means that networks using split DNS SHOULD provide DoH servers which are able to
	provide answers for the internal name space.  
       </t>
       <t>
       Use of third-party DoH servers is not recommended in networks which have split DNS. These
       servers are unlikely to know about the configuration of the local network and will therefore
       be unable to resolve or otherwise properly handle requests for the internal name space. This 
       also presents security and privacy risks. Requests from DoH clients for internal names will
       leak, disclosing sensitive information to an external DoH server which is operated and
       controlled by a third party.  DoH clients on networks using split DNS SHOULD query DoH
       servers which have been configured for that network's internal name space.  
       </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Secure DNS (DNSSEC)">
    <t>
      <xref target="RFC8484">RFC 8484</xref> explains that interactions between a DoH server and
      client benefit from the transport security provided by HTTPS and that DoH does not provide
      message integrity. Put simply, although a DoH client can be sure it received exactly the data
      sent by a DoH server, it does not know if that server is telling the truth. That can only be
      verified by DNSSEC validation, assuming that the DNS data are signed. Therefore a
      security-conscious DoH client SHOULD support DNSSEC and perform DNSSEC validation by
      itself. In some circumstances, a DoH client MAY trust a DoH server to validate signed
      responses on their behalf but MUST take full account of the conseqences of doing so.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Multicast DNS">
	 <t>
	   Need to say something about this and .local
	 </t>
  </section>
</section>


<section title="DoH Impact on Web Behaviour">
  <section title="Browser Caches">
    <t>
      A web browser maintains a cache of recent DNS data. Responses from DoH servers will affect the
      contents of that cache. This presents a security risk because it provides a way for DoH
      servers to arbitrarily manipulate the content of a browser's cache that would not be possible
      with conventional DNS.
    </t>
    <t>
      DoH servers SHOULD NOT send DoH data (i.e. application/dns-message elements) unrelated to the
      request made by a DoH Client. Similarly, a web server SHOULD NOT send DoH data that does not
      correspond to any of the URIs in the HTML which is returned. i.e. If all the URIs on some web
      page are for foo.example.com, the web server SHOULD NOT send application/dns-message elements
      for bar.example.com or example.net. DoH clients SHOULD ignore such unrelated DoH data sent by
      a DoH or web server. DoH clients MUST NOT cache such data.
    </t>
    <t>
      Browser caches MUST respect the TTL in the response DNS RRSet.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Interaction with DoH Unaware Web Proxies">
    <t>
      Placeholder
    </t>
  </section>
    <section title="Interaction with DoH Aware Web Proxies">
    <t>
      DoH aware web proxies MUST respect the TTL in the response DNS RRSet.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="What else?">
    <t>
     There have to be some server PUSH horrors here
    </t>
  </section>
</section>

<section title="Use Cases">
  <section title="DoH server forwarding to a traditional validating resolver:">
    <t>
      Placeholder
    </t>
 </section>
 <section title="DoH server using private dns RRs known only to the DoH server">
   <t>
     Placeholder
   </t>
 </section>
 <section title="DoH server to HTTP server forwarding to a traditional validating resolver:">
   <t>
     Placeholder
   </t>
 </section>
 <section title="DoH server to HTTP server using private dns RRs known only to the DoH server">
   <t>
     Placeholder
   </t>
 </section>

</section>

<section title="Recommendations">
    <t>
      DoH servers MUST NOT create an alternate root.
    </t>
    <t>
      The responses received over DoH MUST be available in the traditional DNS.
    </t>
    <t>
      The DoH server MAY make choices about which RRs to return if it knows more about the network
      topology.
    </t>
    <t>
      The DoH server MAY push useful additional RRs if it knows the client is likely to need them
      soon. Again, they MUST be available in the traditional DNS.
    </t>
    <t>
      DoH servers MUST support DNSSEC.
    </t>
    <t>
      DoH clients SHOULD support DNSSEC.
    </t>
</section>

<section title="Privacy Considerations">
    <t>
      Text goes here
    </t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
  <t>
    Text goes here
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
</section>


<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
	Fill this in later
      </t>
</section>
    
</middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

<back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC2119;
      



    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->
      &RFC2137;
      &RFC2845;
      &RFC7858;
      &RFC8484;
      &RFC8499;

    </references>

    <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
      <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
    </section>

 </back>
</rfc>
